so
I'm thinking about a question suppose you
kind of recognize
the degree to which there's
um
nothing whatsoever
that can be safely that you can care
about see hmm see hmm
but
your mind still cares about things
I wants to like wants to care about
things
and I'm not talking about like
they could be good things that you care
about so what should be done and what should
so what should be done and what should
not be done
so we've got to ask what are the good
things what do you means more
specifically I mean things like
I mean things like
um I don't know
helping other people uh being reconciled
with people you might have heard in the
past family that sort of good thing I
mean so when you say the Mind wants to
care about it does it mean it doesn't
care but you think you should care or it
means it cares but you're finding a
problem with it
it cares uh-huh but you like you know
that you have to abandon
care for even these good things yeah
and like at some point
like at some point
you know
that's that's at some point you have to
stop caring about everything like yeah
yeah colloquially speaking like you you can't
colloquially speaking like you you can't
stop exactly yeah the mind can just lose
interest through becoming this
passionate yeah so that's really the
question um to what degree mine still cares for
um to what degree mine still cares for
things including good things
and that's when you recognize that okay
so you can't tell it to stop yeah you
can psychologize it as much as you want
so the question isn't why doesn't your
mind obey you
why is it not completely pliable to turn
away completely from things so why is it
what do you think it is
why would the mind not be completely
pliable even regards to the subtle
things there's two I think that there's two
there's two I think that there's two
ways one is
like the reason that the whole gradual
training is there is that
yeah exactly you can't just tell your
mind to stop caring about things you
need to kind of develop
let's say certain
like mental strength like to develop
develop virtue develop Central strain
develop the ability to kind of
the ability to kind of
um relinquish things
a relinquish care in regard to things so
that has to be done
through the gradual training there's no
other way to do it
um and that kind of involves
doing it doing the gradual training
while still seeing
the that like there's always has to be
further to go basically there's always
more of it that you can do so you just
have to then stick to the gradual
training and use the presence of these
things as a criteria for there is still
work to be done exactly
um so it's like I don't deal with them
directly I deal with through gradual
gradual training such as virtue preset
sense restraint and then multiple and so
my intention on a day-to-day basis uh
not giving rise not acting towards
distractions on a day-to-day basis and
all of that is making the mind more
pliable generally making the mind more
dispassionate making mind making the
Mind turn away from things on its own
and then when you recognize oh the
things I
care about are still there but there is
no care so that was my second question
was basically what constitutes caring
about things
is the experience of care Pleasant or
unpleasant
fundamentally unpleasant in its core
it's unpleasant it's not quite agreeable
so what is then care is it presence of
thoughts perceptions uh about people
that are close to you that you know that
you feel like you owe them help and so
on or is it you being affected by the
displeasure of it no it's exactly it's
you can have you can still help or you
can still do things let's say yeah you
can still have perception so you can
still care in that sense but not really
care because you're not affected on the
emotional level being detached from the
things that you're doing or the people
that you would you simply not feel it
exactly not feel that discomfort on
account of it you can still care you can
look after dogs you can look after
people you can give you can you can
spend all night not sleeping if they
need help if they're ill but you won't
feel that discomfort of care my care my
burden and that's the difference and the reason
and that's the difference and the reason
why I'm highlighting the difference is
because obviously people can easily
again slot into a view that okay so I
must stop getting the Mind must stop
caring that means I will not even
recognize such thoughts of what used to
be my care no that can equally remain I
mean you had like
anagam is almost a virtual other hands
basically in a household life back in
the Buddha's day when they were looking
after the parents and so on in in caring
for other people they're not really
caring in that sense
so you don't need to abolish the
perception of of Duty of you know paying
back uh what you owe in terms of service and
uh what you owe in terms of service and
help and so on uh on account of not
feeling the discomfort of it and that's
that pliability of the Mind where
basically you stop feeling because the
mind is not perturbed even by things
such as care
such as Duty
so and that's that's exactly that's not
something that can be
um done on that intentional level
yeah so how do you stop caring should
really be rephrased as to how do I stop
being moved by care how do I stop
feeling anything on account of even even
good care yeah
and you stop that by making the Mind
pliable to that extent where there is no
more passion even to those those little
degrees there is no more wanting there left
there is no more wanting there left
and
um so but we still haven't answered the
first question though so why is that in
the mind not pliable
I mean we answered it broadly because
the graduation is not developed fully
but specifically then
how would you then make the mind that's
not sufficiently pliable how would you
make it even more pliable
do you take on more presets or something
no
so you keep the precepts that doesn't
change guarding of the sends those
can you do more of that or less of that
or
can that be improved
I would say it's more about
it's not about um adding specifically
okay if it's preset or it's more like uh
guarding sensitors or it's more this or
it's more of that it's just like
that these things have to be
um
complete and unbroken basically so it's
not about doing doing more of certain
things it's more about like nust not
allowing it it's not quantity it's quality it's
it it's not quantity it's quality it's
quality yeah it's not about it but it
could be both like okay you don't have
you don't need to add more presets and
so on but you could start refining the
principles behind
principle like you yeah I'm guiding my
sense those but then
start refining even that not in a sense
like okay so I will not move I will not
speak I will not blink I will not this
or that but it's like no when I do
choose to do intentional acts within
what I deem to be already God that sends
those they don't go towards greed to the
version to his distraction
well can I refine now discernment of
those intentions within that because
there might be some distractions still
going on to some extent
there might be still some real will
going on as in not going on a rising but
I'm still choosing to act at least to
some degree so you refine that so you do
kind of do more in that sense but within
what you're doing not kind of adding
more in those like uh in a form of
external behaviors and uh and
observances so so that's what always comes down to
so so that's what always comes down to
like sure you might not be engaging with
course uh actions of rooted in lust or
anger or distraction but am I engaging
in subtle ones
am I engaging in certain forms of
distraction or desire that as I said
engaging in means acting out not like do
I have these fleeting thoughts that pass
then on my problem problem is when they
linger around and I choose to welcome
and act upon them exactly I act even and
I I mean that's why I asked about this
caring it's the only reason
does let's say you have a fleeting
thought that arises but even then oh let
me think about this now that constitutes
acting in a way yeah you could do
exactly yeah and let me think about this
now that's another fleeting thought but
then you cannot say okay but before I
think about this now why exactly I need
to know where my intention is rooted so
why do I want to think about it now is
it because I already felt that fleeting
discomfort then now I just try to
explain justify get rid of make it fit
sort it out
so in other words I'm acting out of
trying to get rid of the pain however
fleeting it might be so then you don't
do it for that reason because you
recognize where the intention is rooted
like that's the thing that too that I
think is um at one point you mentioned
it as you were talking there
because again there's things that are
just you know uh
so the things that are taken for granted
as oh yeah this is a good thing to this
is if we're thinking about this is worth
but the only reason is taken for granted
like that
is again because there is already a care
in regards to it so just even to
question or to kind of oh
like wait a second this isn't
necessarily worth thinking about and the
only reason you want to think about it
is because you want to think about it's
about about it actually and because it
pertains to it's yours and it's it's
like oh it's important to me ah that has
to be like kind of relinquished and also
sometimes the mind maybe is already
pliable enough but you're just
overlooking exactly the immediate
presence of care
you're just overlooking the fact that
what you really want to do there is just
get rid of that discomfort and once you
recognize that you stop caring
like in that sense you stop being moved
by it
you don't need to deny the thoughts of
care and help and so on but oh no the
only reason I was still pressured by
carries because to that extent I haven't
understood it
I haven't understood the phenomenon of
care whether it's actually rooted in
simply that discomfort subtle one but
still uncomfortable and I wanted to deal
with it thing I
thing I
just observed that uh I'm kind of
interesting in regard to this is that
like so yeah that discomfort or whatever
so yeah that discomfort or whatever
feeling let's say is involved in care
you can see
see
that that feeling let's say or the even
that thought
or that in that object could not be
there without this body basically of
course it's as I mean that's can be very
it could be abstract let's say but if
it's actually being felt or being seen
then that's basically immediately
kind of undermining the whole basis of
care yes okay but that's like the
contemplation of death exactly your own
death undermines any concern you might
have in regard to the world once you
start feeling
the the the the weight of the
conversational death of the liability to
it and the interesting thing is that
that initially could seem very
like you
you um when you care about something you
don't want to you care about it and you
don't want to lose this and the idea of
like totally abandoning the care is
almost from the point of view of really
caring about things is not pleasant
let's say
but when you reflect that even that care
could not exist without this without
like yeah the senses the eyes being
happening to be there working the ears
happening to work the Mind happened to
work normally
um it's like
it's like
you can't care about it even if you want
to yeah inaccessible
and that's the another item is exactly
what you like so
from the point of view of care
giving up care is unpleasant but the
only reason you you're sort of caring is
because it's unpleasant yeah so to
deferred unpleasantly so you care more
and you you get involved with it you act
further because it's already unpleasant
and that threat of unpleasantness
remaining so
that's also why
have to go forth basically at some point
as in order it's it's much it's harder
to do this completely
while still being
involved on a day-to-day basis with the
things that you've always cared but
that's what sudas often say like it's
hard to live their holy life unblemished
so free from any blemishes however
subtle if you're in a household setting
because yes you can again restrain
yourself from course things and keep lid
on other stuff but fundamentally the
whole environment is still tarnishing
because you know it's all about these
things it's all about these ownerships
and and intimacies and connections and
and that's just the way to deal with it
is to not be in it yeah
a great deal of impurities would be
cleared in that way
this is that suits it kind of reminds me
of that Suitor in majima nikaya 87 born
of affection
and on one occasion
there was a certain householder whose
only son who was loved by him and
pleasing to him had died
because of their death he did not work
or eat he would go to the cemetery and
cry my only son where are you my only
son where are you than that householder
approached the blessed one paid respects
to him and sat to one side
when the household was seated the best
one said to him householded you do not
appear to have a stable mind you appear
to be deranged
says but how could I not be deranged
Ponte my only son who I loved and I was
pleased by has died because of that
death I do not work or eat I go to the
cemetery and cry
that and then the Buddha replies that's
how it is householder that's how it is
householder sorrow grief pain dejection
anguish or born from affection
they come from affection hmm
so I'm going to the West
but they're because that's the that's
the key point there
and what is the affection born of um
um
more and more directly more specifically
acting up
more specifically pleasure pleasure you
will not be affectionate with something
that's unpleasant yeah
yeah his son was pleasing to him
so feeling of pleasure has to be as a
basis for any form of
affection and proliferation and intimacy
and um um
dearness
some some people might say well
I love who I if I abandon
affection for my mother my parents
then I don't care for them anymore you're
I don't care for them anymore you're
saying I mustn't care for them
Perfection yeah
but that's like if I don't have
affection yes then the person needs to
learn the difference I just don't help
them in any way no I don't think about
them I don't do any duties towards them
yeah yeah but as we just said that's not
that's not what care is even even to
begin with care is that emotional being
emotionally affected that's what care
means and you abandon that and you can still
and you abandon that and you can still
help people connect people can't
distinguish that obviously because you
know they most likely don't even keep
the presets let alone tame their mind I
don't know how great
because it's either affection or hate
yeah nothing in between
yeah it's just that's the mode
yeah the kind of categorical modes that
mine basically
Harden into so it's either this or that
it's like okay sure but I'm telling you
there is something in between
and if you're out of Faith practice it
with his teaching instead
taming your mind through the gradual
training that whole domain of in between
will become apparent and then you can
understand how can you have intention
without craving
how can you
care for your parents without feeling
anything towards them
but you can't understand while you're
still at the bottom of the mountain in a
swamp of centrality it's just impossible
you can say no no there's nothing at the
top there well how would you know you're
not there
so that's in a way similar to seeing the
difference between feeling and craving
Yeah well yeah all of these all of these
nuances so to speak would become because
it's all exactly comes down to the uh
feeling not being seen as impermanent
feeling not being understood as
suffering just in and of itself even if
it's a pleasant Feeling Just presence of
feeling means suffering
um and that's exactly how craving is in
regards to Feeling by not understanding
feeling you crave when felt
that's it